哈喽 我是Scott Manley
hello it's Scott Manley here
太空叉上次不幸的意外已经过去一阵子了
it's been a couple of months since SpaceX had their unfortunate anomaly
其间二代龙飞船在超级天龙座发动机的一次测试中炸了
where the dragon 2 capsule was destroyed during a test of the super Draco thrusters
从那之后我们得到的消息很少
since then we haven't had very much information
曾有过一段AV画质的非官方视频泄漏
there was that very unofficial and very potato quality video that was leaked
但昨天之前官方一直没什么公告更新
but official updates were thin on the ground until yesterday
而昨天太空叉开了发布会 宣布他们已经非常确定
when SpaceX issued a press release announcing that they were pretty sure
他们找到了事故原因
they figured out exactly what went wrong
大家可以在他们的网页中找到
now you can read it on their website
或者可以看我用老百姓的话向你们解释这些
or you can watch me try to explain it in words that most people can understand
事故发生在返回舱发动机的一次测试中
so the anomaly occurred during a test of the thrusters on the recovered capsule
该飞船已经去过一次空间站并返回地球
it had gone to the space station and then had recovered
所以太空叉想对其进行一次全面测试
and so they wanted to run a complete test on everything
比如能不能成功点燃天龙座发动机
would it fired the Draco thrusters successfully
但当他们刚打开要用于逃逸系统的高压超级天龙座发动机时 出问题了
but then when they went to turn on the high-pressure super Draco thrusters
that were used in the abort system things went wrong on
飞船一侧的加压氦气突然泄漏爆炸
on one side of the capsule the helium pressure leaked out explosively
然后氧化剂起火
and the oxidizer then followed starting a fire
想解释这一切是如何发生的
to explain exactly how this happened
我们需要了解超级天龙座的管路系统
we have to look at the plumbing of the super Draco thrusters
而我为大家准备了这张很有帮助的图表
and I have some helpful graphics here for you
使用温逗屎画图工具1080P高清渲染出来的
rendered in full 1080p HD resolution in Microsoft Paint
超级天龙座发动机是3D打印生产的双组元挤压供应发动机
the super Draco thrusters are 3d printed bi-propellant pressure fed engines
有燃料和氧化剂
that means that it has a fuel and an oxidizer
通过氦气加压 挤压进发动机
which is forced into the engines by gas pressure from a helium tank
超级天龙座的室压大约是60个大气压
the chamber pressure on the super Draco's is about 60 atmospheres
所以需要很高压的氦气罐
which means you need quite a high pressure helium tank
才能推动燃料和氧化剂
to push the fuel and oxidizer through
故障发生在发动机点火之前
the anomaly happened just before engine ignition
为了给系统加压 氦气阀门已经开启
the helium valve had been opened to pressurize the system
但氧化剂和燃料阀门并未开启
but the oxidizer and fuel valves had not yet opened
所以燃料不会流进发动机
and therefore fuel wouldn't be flowing into the engine
这些阀门是根据指令需求才开启的
now these valves open and close according to command
但还有一组非常重要的阀门
but there's another pair of valves in there that are very important
叫做止回阀
these are automatic check valves
它们只允许液体往一个方向流动
they only flow allow fluid to flow in one direction
这非常重要 因为你不想让液体流回到装氦气的部分
this is critically important because you don't want your liquids flowing back into your gas section
这会导致氦气流过的时候发生“打嗝”
at least might cause burping as the gas flows through the system
更糟糕的是，左侧气体系统的管路是钛合金制造的
even worse the piping in the gas system is titanium typically
然而右侧燃料和氧化剂系统的管路
and whereas the piping in the fuel and oxidiser system
则是不锈钢材料 面对腐蚀性燃料更耐操
is lightly to be stainless steel much more robust against the corrosive fuel
止回阀是靠压力运作的
check valves work based on pressure
当液体从一边流向另一边时会推动阀门开启
when you have a fluid flowing in one direction it pushes the valve open
而反向流动的话会推动阀门关闭
when the pressure is in the reverse direction it pushes the valve closed
从而阻止逆流
and it stops the flow
然而在测试中出现了些意外
however during the test something didn't work quite right
或许是发生在燃料加注时
and while it was being either with fuel was being loaded
又或许是燃料氧化剂都加满以后在罐子里的时候
or while it was just sitting around with their oxidizer in the tanks
其中一部分逆流泄漏通过了止回阀
some of that began to leak backwards through the check valve
实际上这不是没有先例的
now this is actually not unprecedented
燃料总会漏过去一点 会在氦气管道中有少量残留
but anyway that would leak through and it collected at a low spot in the helium piping
之后当氦气阀开启 氦气沿着左边的管道流经整个系统
so when the helium valve was opened and the helium began to flow through the system
而上面氧化剂那条路遇到了那一小块栓塞
and the oxidizer loop it encountered this blob of fuel which was blocking the pipe
当高压氦气遇到栓塞并推动其前进时
and when that high pressure helium encountered that it pushed it along the pipe
会像子弹一样把它射出去
exactly like a bullet is pushed down the barrel of a gun
的确有像左边氦气系统那样高压的气步枪
there are actually high-powered air rifles are nearly as high pressure as this helium system
且因氦气的原子量小
and helium because of its lower atomic mass
移动速度会更快
actually moves things even faster
氧化剂栓塞会在几毫秒内通过左边的管路
it takes milliseconds for that blob of oxidizer to find its way through the system
像子弹一样直冲止回阀
and run into that one-way check valve with the force of a bullet
不但其动能足以摧毁止回阀
not only is the momentum and kinetic energy enough to shatter the valve components
同时四氧化二氮还是强氧化剂
but because dinitrogen tetroxide is a highly oxidizing material
且该系统的一些材料是可燃的
and because some of the metals in the system are combustible
于是产生了燃烧 摧毁了管路并起火
this actually starts a metal fire so the pipe ruptures and the fire is started
一旦开始 钛就会很猛烈地燃烧
once it gets started titanium burns very very well
从泄漏的视频中我们能看到
now what we saw in that leaked video
最开始是一侧炸开 一股高压氦气冒出
was initially the side blowing off and a cloud of high pressure helium coming out
而氦气就是加压让其快速移动的物质
the helium is the thing that is pressurized it's moving fast
燃料和氧化剂系统还未被加压
the fuel and oxidizer system those haven't been properly pressurized
所以它们流出的速度会慢得多
so those will come out but they will come out a lot more slowly
整个过程只有几秒
it only takes a few seconds though
有了燃烧 又有很多高能物质
because you've got this fire and you've got a lot of high-energy events
泄漏一开始就会产生燃烧
and once that starts leaking you have a fire already
而烧掉的不只是燃料
and it will burn using not just the fuel
还有飞船本身制造所用的材料
but it will also burn using the materials that were the capsule is manufactured from
加压罐体是碳纤维缠绕的 管路中有金属钛
the pressure vessels are coated in carbon fiber the plumbing may contain titanium
这种情况下铝也会跟着燃烧
aluminium at this the hull will burn as well under the circumstances
不过好消息是太空叉已经想出解决办法 NASA也通过了
so the good news is that SpaceX have already come up with a fix NASA is ok with it
太空叉决定使用爆破隔膜替换止回阀
they're gonna replace these check valves with burst disks
那你肯定会问他们早干嘛来着
why didn't use burst disks in the first place I hear you ask
呃……因为爆破隔膜没法被测试
well burst disks are one use items and they cannot be tested
因为测试完了就废了
because they destroyed themselves in the process
而太空叉又有着众所周知的 使用可被反复测试的机械系统的企业文化
and SpaceX has historically preferred to have mechanical systems that can be tested repeatedly
说到测试
and you know when we're talking about testing
我想调查小组发现钛和其他物质发生罕见的燃烧现象时一定很有趣
I think it would have been fun to be on the team
我想调查小组研究钛和其他物质发生罕见的燃烧现象时一定很有趣
that tried to figure out how they would burn titanium and various other things
同时有趣的是超级天龙座发动机这次成功甩锅了
also amusingly there were survivors the super Draco thrusters that were initially blamed
你们懂的 这么多人唱衰3D打印的情况下成功甩锅
those survived just fine which you know for other people that criticize 3d printing
目前看来3D打印发动机燃烧室结果很不错
it seems to have worked just fine with the super Draco thrust chambers
最后 这次事故还让我们想起当年的火星观察者号
and with this failure brought to mind an old spacecraft called Mars Observer
它在即将进行近火制动的时候失去联系
that would they lost contact with it
as it was about to perform a thruster burn on his way to Mars
虽然最后没有任何证据或残骸
and while obviously there was no evidence or materials to recover
但调查小组结论认为失去联系的最可能的解释就是
the investigation board concluded that the most likely explanation for the loss of contact
四氧化二氮泄漏过止回阀 回流进加压系统
was that nitrogen tetroxide had leaked past the check valve into the pressurization system
并和钛合金反应或者引发其他问题
and either reacted with titanium or caused some other problem
最终摧毁管路 摧毁探测器
that ultimately ruptured the pipes and caused the loss of the spacecraft
按你胃 换了爆破隔膜后
anyway with the burst disk changed
太空叉对他们未来几个月后飞行中发射中止测试很有信心
SpaceX are confident that they can fly their in-flight abort in the next few months
同时也弱弱的希望
and the holding onto some hope
他们能在今年年底前送宇航员去国际空间站
that they might actually launch a crew to the space station before the end of the year
当然 这不但要看到时候飞船是否组装完成
but a lot of that will also depend on not just them getting their spacecraft together
也要看空间站上有没有位置 毕竟上面车位紧张
but also there being a slot available in the space stations very busy parking management
希望龙飞船早日上天
so we hope to see dragon to fly soon
我是Scott Manley 感谢观看 祝一路顺风~
until then I'm Scott Manley fly safe